hello everyone hopefully third time is
the
charm first time I got Co we were trying
to do this H banana smoothies thing and
then just today tried to do it as part
of a live Q&A and technologically it all
failed so although unfortunately this
won't be live won't be able to take
questions but I will get this
information out there um and so
hopefully this will work fingers
crossed all right okay well so the first
part of this will sound familiar who
were watching on YouTube or Facebook
until it all collapsed but now you'll
actually be able to see the PDFs
hopefully actually see the studies that
I'm talking about
okay we all know there are recommended
daily intakes of essential nutrients
like vitamins to prevent deficiencies
but
recently hopefully you can see that but
recently the first dietary
recommendation for a bioactive food
compound was published bioactive food
compounds as you can see in green here
um are not necessary for basic human
needs but may have health benefits for
example these PL metabolites here in red
known as
flavonoids flavonoids are a type of
polyphenol which are uh which of which
the most commonly consumed one is these
flaven thols also known as just
flavanols a review of the literature
here up in
blue um suggests that intake of 400 to
600 milligrams a day of these flavonol
would be beneficial for cardiovascular
protection such as here in red uh
potential for improving blood pressure
cholesterol blood sugars right and now
note here in
Gray um that this is specifically a food
guideline not a supplement guideline
though really it's actually more like a
beverage guideline since if you look at
the uh zoom out a little bit there um uh
if you look at the primary sources it's
really tea green or black is the easiest
way to reach those levels though there
certainly some in a variety of berries
and cocoa however
done there's an enzyme called polyphenol
oxidase that can break down these
wonderful polyphenols like
flavonoids that is what makes certain
fruits and vegetables as you can see
here in in green brown when you cut them
uh such as bananas and potatoes now why
would a plant do that to it itself well
apparently it is um a defense
mechanism um it's part of the plants
immune system as you can see there in
Orange um and uh when exposed to
oxygen um what happens is that
polyphenol oxidates can oxidize
polyphenols into these breakdown
products which have
antimicrobial activity
so when a banana gets bruised for
example uh they're in Gray you cut or
you cut open avocado or something the
polyphenol oxidases can start oxidizing
polyphenols into these defensive
compounds that can glom together here in
red um forming a dark compound called
melanin same class of compounds that
darkens the skin of banana also darkens
our skin too okay so no problem we can
just not eat bananas that have turned
brown right because that's Visual
Evidence that many of the polyphenols
have been lost ah but what if
you mix that banana which you know is
filled with that polyphenol oxidase
enzyme in a smoothie with polyphenol
rich foods like berries or cocoa might
that might that end why you end up with
less nutrition well big chocolate funded
researchers sought to find out
and so what they did is they put a about
a half cup of Coco worth of cocoa
flavanol into in a banana containing
smoothie compared to the same amount in
a berry smoothie with no banana so here
is a
measure okay so here um is a measure of
how many cocoa flavanol make it into
your bloodstream um within hours 1 two 3
three four five six hours after eating
uh the chocy berry smoothie compared to
the same amount of cocoa blended into
a banana smoothie right so the same
amount of those cocoa goodies but it's
almost as if there was no cocoa in there
at all presumably because the banana
enzymes chopped up all the chocolate
goodies
um let's not presume though um they
Blended up that uh chocolatey banana
smoothie again um which was just banana
almond milk cocoa flavanol and then they
just measured the level of flavanol as
the Smoothie sat for an
hour check it out that is what happened
the cocoa flavanol plumed more than
90% a halflife of about about 10 10
minutes um uh so uh so every 10 minutes
the levels of polyphenols drop in half
now how do we know it was for sure it
was this polyphenol oxidase enzyme
because then if you add um various
polyphenol
Inhibitors um then uh what um then uh
then they block the effect okay so no
problem if you add bananas to your
smoothies just you have to chug them
down before the enzyme does its job
right I mean presumably the enzyme would
be
deactivated when it hit the Acid Bath of
our stomach but you don't know until you
put it to the test and I love that the
research did all this all these extra
steps here uh so here you are in in in
green here what they did is this time
they had study participants um alternate
sips alternate sips U between a straight
banana almond milk smoothie um and like
chocolate milk chocolate flavonoids plus
the almond milk right so there was no
premixing uh in the blender between the
banana enzyme and the flavanol just
mixing in the
stomach such such kind of an elegant
research move Okay
so
here's how many cocoa
flavanols here we go here's how many
cocoa flavonol make it in your
bloodstream um uh sipping the uh
chocolate milk Alone um here with these
kind of brown greenish Brown uh uh uh
little
um data here um and then here is when
it's mixing just in the stomach when
you're alternating SS with the banana
smoothie um and so uh that you get 37%
Less in your bloodstream showing that
the banana enzyme can still do some
polyphenol damage in your
stomach um it's starting to get dark and
so my screen's GNA start to yellow
because I cut out that the blue blocker
um a Blue Block effect but I just turned
that off so we should be good
okay um and indeed um in a simulated
stomach acid
um in a in kind of simulated stomach
acid conditions um yes the polyphenol
oxidase um is indeed down but not out
okay
so yeah um if you drink some smoothie
with a banana and it's better not to let
it sit around but even if you drink it
immediately you can get less polyphenols
in your system than if you had have
skipped the
banana all right all right but bananas
make smoothies so rich and creamy I mean
anything we can add to the Smoothie to
counter the banana enzymes effects
that's exactly what I'll cover next but
not really next because that's what I
would have said in the video but we're
all gonna be covering right here right
now um actually it's uh let me turn down
that light a little bit
um oh it's not showing up all right it's
okay it's okay all
right
um let me just take a few seconds though
uh before I continue um with this story
to ask for your help um we usually made
this a YouTube fundraiser but now it's
not really on YouTube but um if you're
watching this on nutritionfacts.org um
uh and you find this valuable please
consider making a tax deductible
donation to support this wonderful work
um uh and uh and uh so as a kind of end
of year show of thanks uh we you know we
don't accept money from food companies
or supplement companies or you know
kitchen Gizmo companies or anything like
that just individual donors like you so
thank you so much for your support okay
back to our regularly scheduled program
there's one food that has even more
polyphenol ox activities in banana and
it's a vegetable that's not a
potato what vegetable turns brown that's
not a white potato all right let's go
look uh
okay
20 um let's find
out aha here we go so here's polyphenol
polyphenol oxidase activity in various
fruits and vegetables and oh oh white
mushrooms white button mushrooms as you
can see have more polyphenol uh um um
oxid activity than even bananas now for
those of you thinking uh don't worry I
don't think I'm expect to be adding any
mushrooms into my smoothies anytime soon
now some people do add avocados um to
smoothies um or make like a chocolate
avocado pudding and here's the question
what if you eat mushrooms with a meal
packed with polyphenol rich foods right
might it mix in your stomach and
decrease the absorption like the an
thein in red cabbage or berries for
dessert right um and look you could also
be having some potatoes with your meal
or eggplant um with your meal which also
as you can see contains it um now note
though however this is is for fresh
produce right so you know we're not
worrying about the eggplant potatoes um
and uh the enzyme is
utterly destroyed by cooking so this is
a inactivation of the mushroom uh
polyphenol oxidates inam and as you can
see um it plummets
readily um and look remember we should
be cooking our mushrooms anyway right
because of the gutin most of our
mushrooms uh you don't have to cook
oyster mushrooms but the white and
criminy and portella mushrooms right so
problem solved right they uh you know so
you don't have to worry about cooked
potatoes cooked eggplant cooked
mushrooms okay uh but who wants to cook
their bananas though right what else
could we put in a smoothie instead my
personal favorite is mango which you buy
Frozen when it's not in season uh do we
have to worry about that having a
polyphenol eating enzyme s well what
happens when you cut open a mango does
it go Brown no it doesn't go Brown which
should show you um exactly um what this
data uh shows here and that
is uh if you
look um that um mango right here has oh
maybe 500 times less than that banana
this is polyphenol o um in activity this
is the activity of that enzyme that
destroys polyphenols like flavonoids
right now the Apple certainly doesn't um
uh doesn't surprise me right because
what what happens with apples turns
brown but what is with this be greens I
did not know about that so if you're
making a green smoothie better use
something like kale which has enzyme
levels so low they're below the level of
detection
okay uh
but boy the Smoothie study raises so
many interesting questions right so uh
what forget smoothies should you not add
bananas to your oatmeal right because
the bananas in your stomach would mix
with like the berries or the cocoa that
you put in your oatmeal um and indeed um
that is what we should expect so I no
longer add bananas to my cran chocolate
pomegranate breakfast bowl um that was
one of my cooking videos if you missed
it um uh and uh since you know I don't
want to lose any of those polyphenols
there's so many wonderful ingredients in
that I don't want to lose any don't want
any of those destroyed that 37% decrease
in your stomach um when it all mixes
with that enzyme okay but what if you're
not making something
chocolaty
the um this study W only tested the
effects of the enzyme on Coco flavonol
like they didn't check to see if like
mixing bananas with berries would affect
the berry phytonutrients but the
presumption is that it would um and so H
what does that mean for like ready to
drink bottled smoothie drinks that you
might find in the store right that may
be sitting on the shelf well if it's
been pasteurized then it should be okay
right because the heat destroys that
enzyme uh that's vegetables are blanched
you know before they're frozen to
destroy the enzymes even just
heating uh bananas to 70 let me see
table
two that's figure two I'm looking for oh
yeah yeah yeah
yeah uh okay um so here we're in this is
inactivation methods for that enzyme of
bananas even just heating um in here
we're looking at the T2
data right
here um even just heating banana to like
70 degrees C which is like hot tea 70
degrees CSUS for two minutes in the
presence of vitamin C and citric acid
which might come from lemon juice for
example would suppress the enzyme by
80% I'm not suggesting drinking hot
smoothies but rather that those
pasteurized smoothie drinks depending on
the ingredients may not have the same
problem as fresh made smoothies uh what
about just the adding the vitamin C and
citric acid alone like putting lemon
juice in your smoothie that is the T1 oh
here let me move this over that's the T1
data here um and as you can see it only
Cuts enzy activity by about 133% without
the heating step however it does work
wonders for
apples so um as you can see here um a a
cut Apple um you just add some lemon
juice and you can cut that activity
nearly in half um explaining why adding
lemon juice to your fruit salad you know
keeps the apples and your fruit salad
from turning brown okay anything we can
add to a banana smoothie to inhibit the
enzyme so we can still use bananas but
somehow block the enzyme well they Ed to
put
um blue there we go they use to put
sulfites in fresh fruits and vegetables
to block that enzyme until they were
banned in
1986 following cases of sulfite induced
asthma they are still used in dried
fruit though to prevent Browning the
apricots on the left um are sulfured
with sulfites and the ones on the right
are not um it's purely cosmetic you want
to get the unsulfured so you don't have
to worry about um sulfite induced
respiratory problems what um so okay
sulfites are kind of OD off the table um
but what
about other what about natural agents
what can we do for natural anti-browning
agents to block this puppy well as you
can see in Orange there onion extracts
can prevent the Browning of of uh of
pears uh and you see in in Gray both
fresh and cooked onion juice um both
work but there has got to be something
better for your smoothies and
indeed pineapple juice as you can see in
in purple there does seem to help keep
apples from browning um and bananas too
uh for that matter but that was after
soaking in pineapple juice for three
days so it's not clear if it would work
right away um there was a study um here
underlined in yellow um comparing lemon
juice and white wine to prevent Browning
in pastry dough uh you've heard of hard
cider hard Seltzer well the lemon juice
it appears um beat out the wine so uh
better a Lemon Squeeze than drinking a
hard
smoothie anyway okay so that's the let
me stop sharing here that's the
story on bananas and smooth so should
you not eat bananas no you can eat
bananas anytime you just don't want to
eat bananas you just want to have the
bananas in your stomach at the same time
you have other healthy foods like
berries cocoa tea um and so but like as
a snack on its own totally fine uh but
uh smooth the aside still um you could
uh you could impair some of the um uh
you could destroy some of the
phytonutrients if you had it in your
stomach at the same time as meal and
same thing with uh you know uh uncooked
mushrooms and some of those other things
oh like the the the avocado um anyway
I'm sure this raised a lots of questions
and I was hoping to take lots of
questions today that was before the the
tech disaster but uh certainly be happy
to answer next time I do Q&A thank you
so much everyone thank you for everyone
who decided to support us this year um
this will actually this topic will
actually be up in actual video on
nutritionfacts.org all polished and
fancy um but didn't want to wait for you
to get this important information have a
good
night